You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we take a critical look
at one of the foods people
have trouble cutting down on.
We start with the simple question:
is cheese really bad for you?
In a series of videos I did
about saturated fat,
I talked about a major campaign
launched by the global dairy industry
to neutralize the negative image
of milkfat among regulators
and health professionals
as related to heart disease.
That campaign continues to
this day with the publication of
a meta-analysis demonstrating neutral,
meaning non-harmful associations,
between dairy products and
cardiovascular disease and death.
OK, well first of all, how do
we know the dairy industry
had anything to do with this study?
Well, it was published in a
journal that forces authors
to disclose financial
conflicts of interest.
Let's see, what they divulged.
Dairy, dairy, dairy, dairy,
dairy, dairy, the 4th largest
dairy company in the world,
dairy, dairy, milk, beer, soda,
McDonald's, dairy, dairy,
dairy, dairy, dairy.
Oh, and the study itself was explicitly
funded by dairy, dairy, dairy.
OK, then.
The other big new one was this,
suggesting that a little bit of cheese
every day isn't just neutral,
but actually good for you.
And they make it clear that they
have no conflicts of interest;
they're just employees of
the Yili Innovation Center
and the Yili R&D Center, you know,
China's largest dairy producer,
making it one of the world's
largest dairy companies.
OK, but how can cheese consumption be
associated with better health outcomes?
Well, most of these studies
were from Europe,
where cheese consumption is associated
with a higher socioeconomic status.
See, in Europe they're not eating
Cheez Whiz and Velveeta.
Cheese is generally an expensive
product, and so who eats cheese?
Those with higher paying jobs,
higher socioeconomic strata,
higher education levels,
all of which are associated
with better health outcomes,
which may have nothing to do
with their cheese consumption.
Higher socioeconomic
groups also consume
more fruits and vegetables,
and more candies.
So I bet you could
do a population study
and show candy consumption is
associated with better health.
Shh, don't tell the National
Confectioner's Association.
Too late!
Did you know that candy consumers
have lower levels of inflammation,
a 14% decreased risk
of elevated blood pressure?
Brought to you by the candy industry
and the USDA, our government,
which props up the sugar industry
to the tune of a billion dollars a year.
It's like when our tax dollars
are used to buy up surplus cheese.
Paul Shapiro wrote a great editorial.
Imagine the headline "Government
Buys $20 Million in Surplus Pepsi,"
our hard-earned tax dollars buying
up millions of unwanted cola cans,
all as a favor to the
flailing soda industry,
which just kept producing
drinks no one wanted.
As outrageous as such a government
handout to the soda industry would be,
that's exactly what the USDA
is doing for the dairy industry.
Michele Simon did a great
report on how our government
colludes with the industry
to promote dairy junk foods.
The federal government administers
"check-off programs"
to promote milk and dairy.
McDonald's has six dedicated dairy
checkoff program employees
at its corporate headquarters to
try to squeeze in more cheese.
That's how we got
double steak quesadillas.
That's how we got 3-Cheese
Stuffed Crust Pizza,
complete with a
"Summer of Cheese."
These funds are being
used to promote foods
that contribute to
the very diseases
our federal government is
allegedly trying to prevent.
Does it make sense
to tell Americans
to avoid foods high in salt,
sugar, and saturated fat,
while engaging in the promotion
of those same foods?
Look, the meat and dairy industries can
do what they like with their own money,
but the public power of taxation
should be used for the public good,
not to support the dairy
and candy industries.
In our next story, we compare
dairy to other foods
for heart attack
and stroke risk.
When industry-funded studies
suggest their products
have neutral health effects,
or even beneficial,
one question you always have
to ask is compared to what?
Is cheese healthy?
Compared to what?
If you're sitting down to make a
sandwich, cheese is probably healthy—
compared to bologna—but compared
to peanut butter? No way.
That's the point Walt Willet made,
former chair of nutrition at Harvard.
To conclude that dairy foods are
"neutral" could be misleading, as
it could be misinterpreted to mean that
increasing consumption of dairy foods
would have no effects on
cardiovascular disease or mortality.
Lost is that the health
effects of increasing
or decreasing consumption
of dairy foods would depend
importantly on the specific foods
that are substituted for dairy foods.
Like what are you going
to put on your salad?
Cheese would be healthy compared
to bacon, but not compared to nuts.
See, consumption of
nuts or plant protein
has been found to be
protectively associated
with the risk of coronary heart
disease and type 2 diabetes.
In contrast, intake of red meat,
for example, has been associated
with increased risk.
Thus, it's reasonable to assume that
the lack of association with dairy foods
could put them somewhere in the
middle of a spectrum of healthfulness,
but certainly not an optimal
source of energy or protein.
More broadly, the available
evidence supports policies
that limit dairy production
and encourages production
of healthier sources
of proteins and fats.
He wasn't just speculating.
This was based on three famous Harvard
studies involving hundreds of thousands
of men and women exceeding
5 million person-years of follow-up.
This was really the first large-scale
prospective study to examine dairy fat
intake, compared to other types of fat in
relation to heart attack and stroke risk.
So replacing like 100 calories
of fat worth of cheese
with 100 calories of fat worth
of peanut butter on a daily basis
might reduce risk up to 24%,
whereas substitution with other
animal fats might make things worse.
Here's how it breaks
down for heart disease.
Swapping dairy fat for like
vegetable oil would be associated
with a decrease in disease risk, whereas
swapping dairy for meat increases risk.
Dairy fat calories may be as
bad or worse as straight sugar.
The lowest risk would entail swapping
to a whole plant food, like whole grains.
Yeah, dairy products
are a major contributor
to the saturated fat in the diet
and have thus been targeted as
one of the main dietary causes of, you
know, the #1 killer of men and women.
But the dairy industry
likes to argue
there are other things in dairy products
like fermentation by-products
in cheese that could counteract
the saturated fat effects,
all part of an explicit campaign by
the dairy industry to neutralize
the negative image of milkfat among
regulators and health professionals.
If Global Dairy Platform looks familiar,
they were one of the funders
of the milk-and-dairy-is-neutral study,
trotting out their dairy-fat-
is-counteracted notion.
To which the American Heart
Association responds that
no information from controlled
studies supports the assertion
that fermentation adds
beneficial nutrients to cheese
that somehow counteract the
harmful effects of the saturated fat.
We need to cut down on
dairy, meat, coconut oil,
no matter what their
respective industries say.
In fact, that's the reason the
American Heart Association
felt that they needed to release this
special Presidential Advisory in 2017.
They wanted to set the record straight
on why well-conducted scientific research
overwhelmingly supports limiting
saturated fat in the diet.
Finally today, we look at how
the meat and dairy industries
design studies showing
their products have neutral
or even beneficial effects on
cholesterol and inflammation.
But what about
this interventional study?
A randomized, crossover trial which
compared a high-fat cheese diet,
to a high-fat meat diet,
to a low-fat diet.
A high cheese diet: CHEESE,
which is loaded with saturated fat,
a high meat diet: MEAT, which
is loaded with saturated fat,
versus CARB, a low-fat diet,
and people ended up with
the same cholesterol levels.
Let's see how they did it.
Half the study was paid for
in part by the dairy industry,
and the other half paid for by
dairy, dairy, dairy, and dairy.
If you're the dairy industry, and
you're trying to design a study
to show that a high cheese diet
doesn't raise cholesterol,
how would you go
about doing that?
The beef industry was in the
same pickle as the cheese industry.
Beef has saturated fat,
which raises cholesterol,
which raises the risk of
dying from our #1 killer.
What's an industry to do?
So they designed a study where they
added beef, and cholesterols went down.
How is that possible?
They did this by cutting out so much
dairy, pork, poultry, fish, and eggs
that their overall saturated
fat intake was cut in half.
They cut saturated fat levels in half
and the cholesterol levels went down.
Well, duh.
They could
have swapped in Twinkies
and said snack cakes lower your
cholesterol, or frosting or anything.
OK, so now that
you know the trick,
let's go back to this study.
How are you going to get
a high-fat cheese diet,
and a high-fat meat diet
to have anywhere near the
same saturated fat level
as a diet with neither, unless...
Wait, don't tell me.
What, they added coconut oil
or something to the other diet?
They added so much
coconut oil and cookies
to the so-called low fat diet
that they were able to sufficiently
raise the level of saturated fat
to cause a similar
rise in cholesterol.
That's now you can make sure
a cheese or meat-rich diet
look like it doesn't
raise cholesterol.
That reminds me of the desperation
evident in this study
that compared the effects
of dairy cheddar cheese to a nondairy
cheddar cheese called Daiya.
Milk consumption has
plummeted in recent years
as people have discovered
plant-based alternatives
like soymilk and almond milk,
and now there's plant-based
cheese alternatives?
What's the National Dairy Council to do?
How are you going to design a study
that shows it's healthier to eat cheese,
design a study where cheese causes less
inflammation than the vegan alternative?
They got their work
cut out for them.
Daiya is no health
food by any stretch,
but definitely three times less
saturated fat than cow cheese.
So, I give up.
How could you possibly show
more inflammation from Daiya?
Well, there is one fat that may cause
more inflammation that milk fat: palm oil.
In fact, it may raise
cholesterol levels
as much as trans-fat laden
partially hydrogenated oil.
Yeah, but what, are you telling me
they like slipped the Daiya group
some extra palm oil on the side?
Yes, can you believe it?
They compared cheese
to Daiya plus palm oil,
so much extra palm oil that the
vegan alternative meal ended up
having the same amount of
saturated fat as the cheese meal.
That's like proving tofu is worse
than beef by doing a study
where they compared a beef burger
to a tofu patty stuffed with lard.
Oh, wait, the meat industry
already did that, but at least
they had the decency to concede
that replacement of meat
by tofu in the habitual diet
would probably not usually be
accompanied by the addition of lard.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.